<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints support, set out in a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament. At a publick fast, 29. Iune, 1642. By William Gouge.</title>
            <author>Gouge, William, 1578-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E107_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873610</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873610</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 19:E107[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints support, set out in a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament. At a publick fast, 29. Iune, 1642. By William Gouge.</title>
                  <author>Gouge, William, 1578-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Joshua Kirton at his Shop in Pauls Church-yard at the Signe of the white Horse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLII. [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of first leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the late fast before the Commons House of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Nehemiah V, 19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterian Church --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="Parliamentary_order">
            <pb facs="tcp:155989:1"/>
            <opener>
               <date>Die Mercurij, 29. Iunij, 1642.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the
COMMONS now aſſembled in
PARLIAMENT, That Sir <hi>Thomas
Barrington</hi> doe returne thanks to
Doctor <hi>Gouge</hi> for the great pains he
took in his Sermon this day preach't
at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> at
the intreaty of the COMMONS
Houſe of PARLIAMENT, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the day of the publike Faſt, and
that he be deſired to Print his. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;
and that no man preſume to
print it, but ſuch as he ſhall appoint,
till the Houſe ſhall take further Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>H. Elſynge,</hi> Cler. Parl, D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I Appoint <hi>Ioſhua Kirton</hi> to Print the fore-ſaid
Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM GOUGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155989:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
SAINTS
SVPPORT,
<hi>Set out in</hi>
A SERMON PREACHED
Before the Honourable Houſe of
COMMONS aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>At a publick Faſt, 29. <hi>Iune,</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Gouge.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ECCLUS. 49. 13.</bibl>
               <p>Among the Elect was <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> whoſe renown is great.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Joſhua Kirton</hi> at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi>
Church-yard at the Signe of the white Horſe,
MDCXLII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:155989:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155989:2"/>
            <head>TO THE
HONOVRABLE HOVSE
of COMMONS aſſembled
in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt worthy Patriots,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Wiſe-man among his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
approved</hi> Proverbes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov</hi> 25 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iuxta modus ſuos. Merc. Quibus modia dici debet <hi>V<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> Tempore, ſuo. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>hath this choyce one,</hi> A
word ſpoaken upon his
wheeles (<hi>ſo runnes the
Originall, or</hi> ſet upon his
meaſures, <hi>that is, as our Engliſh not unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
hath tranſlated it,</hi> fitly ſpoken) A word
fitly ſpoken, is the like Apples of Gold in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutres
<pb facs="tcp:155989:3"/>
of ſilver; <hi>pretious and pleaſant. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,
as</hi> golden Apples: <hi>pleaſant</hi> as yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
Gold curiouſly wrought and artificially wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
in white Silver.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Proverbe</hi> turned my minde to thinke
of ſome ſeaſonable Theame, after notice was
given me, that by your Order, which to mee
is a Law, I was deputed to preach before
your Honourable Aſſembly. And I thinke I
have hit upon a fit Subject, were I fit and able
to handle it as it is meet to be handled in ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</p>
            <p>It is the Patterne of a good Patriot.</p>
            <p>A point pertinent in <hi>Generall</hi> and <hi>Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Generall,</hi> a Patterne or Example regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
and approoved in Sacred Scripture,
ſhews</p>
            <p>1. What is the good and acceptable will of God.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="*" place="margin">Si inveniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur exempla quae nos per re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctan ducunt viam, ſequen. da ſunt. <hi>Hier.</hi> ad celant.</note> What in like caſe others are bound to doe.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="†" place="margin">Excitamur in ipem, qua nos e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ita poſſe vivere, qui ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ſum ex eo quod aliqui homines ita vixerunt, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimè deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Aug</hi> de Trin. l. 8. c. 9.</note> What may be done by ſuch as will thorowly
ſet themſelves to it.</p>
            <p>4. VVhat, when it is ſo done, may be pleaded
in an humble-ſelf-denying manner before God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:155989:3"/>
In <hi>Particular</hi> this Example of <hi>Nehemiah</hi>
ſhewes,</p>
            <p>1. VVho is a good Patriot.</p>
            <p>2. How he ought to behave himſelfe.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Plut</hi> de Lib inſtit.</note> VVhat difficulties and dangers attend him.</p>
            <p>4. VVhat oppoſition and contradiction hee is
like to meet with.</p>
            <p>5. VVhat reſolutions become him.</p>
            <p>6. On whom his confidence is to be placed.</p>
            <p>Our times are in many things not much unlike to
the time wherein <hi>Nehemiah</hi> came to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Grievances in State.</p>
            <p>Corruptions in Church.</p>
            <p>He did as much as in him lay (and that indeed
was very much) for redreſſing of the one, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving
of the other.</p>
            <p>His patterne is not onely an <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> to
teach what is to be done: or an <hi>Incitation</hi> to ſtir
up ſuch as know what is to be done: but alſo a <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi>
and <hi>Approbation</hi> of ſuch as doe as
he did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And they may looke for ſuch an end,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Ioſeph An<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iq. Iul. l. 11. c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>as</hi> Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus
<hi>teſtifies that</hi> Nehemiah <hi>had. His teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
is this,</hi> When <hi>Nehemiah</hi> had done moſt
<pb facs="tcp:155989:4"/>
magnificently many good things worthy of
praiſe, being an old man he died, and leſt
behind him the name of a gracious, juſt and
bountifull man toward his owne Nation.</p>
            <p>The Lord encline our great Kings heart to you, as
he did the heart of <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> King to him, and
ſo worke by you, as he did by him: that every of
you may with ſuch confidence ſay to your God, as he
did to his, <hi>Thinke on me, my GOD for good,</hi>
according <hi>to all that I have done for this Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
This is, this ſhall be, the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your daily Oratour<lb/>
                  <hi>William Gouge.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155989:4"/>
            <head>A
SERMON PREACHED
Before the Honourable Houſe of
COMMONS, at the celebration of a
FAST 29. Iune, 1642.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>NEHEM. 5. 19.</bibl>
                  <p>Thinke upon me, my God, for good, according
to all that I have done for this people.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe two motives which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
the good Patriot <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi>
to preferre this Petition
to his God, have enduced
me to chooſe it for my Text,
to handle it before ſo many
worthy Patriots as are now
met together to preſent their
humble ſupplications to their God.</p>
            <p>The two motives were theſe,</p>
            <p>1. The many, great, good things which he had
done for the Church and State.</p>
            <p>2. The many, great, deſperate dangers which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155989:5"/>
he had met with, and knew he ſhould further meet
with in proſecuting his good beginnings.</p>
            <p>Whether there be not at this time the like occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
for the repreſentative body of this Kingdome,
as one man, to pray and ſay, <hi>Thinke upon me my God
for good, according to all that I have done for this
people,</hi> let the times judge.</p>
            <p>To this Text the more diligent heed is to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
in that it containeth the laſt memorable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
which the Holy Ghoſt ſaw meet to commend
to his Church in the old Teſtament. For the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
part of it (wherein the maine ſubſtance of the
whole lyeth) is repeated in the laſt clauſe of this
Booke,<note place="margin">Neh. 13. 31.</note> which is the laſt Booke of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
For all the Propheſies regiſtred in the old
Teſtament were before <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time: which
thus appeareth. All but the three laſt were before
the Captivity of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Babylon.</hi> Two of thoſe
laſt three,<note place="margin">Ezr. 5. 1. Hag. 1. 1. Zech. 1. 1.—7. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zechary</hi> uttered their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies
about the time that the Temple was finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
in the foure firſt yeares of <hi>Darius</hi> his reigne.
<hi>Malachi</hi> who is the laſt of all the Prophets prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied
anone after the Temple was built,<note place="margin">Malachi, id eſt Eſdras, poſt Aggeum &amp; Zechariam, qui ſub Dario pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet averunt, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſse credendus eſt Hier in pro in Malach. Lege Clem A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex Strom. l 1.</note> as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
by the maine ſcope of his Prophecy: So as
he may well be thought to have uttered his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie
in the daies of <hi>Darius,</hi> or in that time of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi>
reigne, wherein <hi>Ezra</hi> came firſt to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
For <hi>Malachi</hi> is ſuppoſed to be <hi>Ezra,</hi> and
called <hi>Malachi,</hi> becauſe he was the Lords Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>As for the booke of <hi>Heſter,</hi> though it be placed
after this of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> yet is it an Hiſtory of many
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155989:5"/>
yeares before: for the things therin recorded were
in the reigne of <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſt. 1. 1.</note> of whom mention is
made, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 4. 6. He ended his daies foureſcore
yeares before <hi>Nehemiah</hi> came to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> The
compiler of the bookes of the old Teſtament, had
more reſpect of the order of <hi>matter</hi> then of <hi>time</hi> in
placing <hi>Eſter</hi> after <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> For <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi>
are one continued Hiſtory, which ſets downe
the reſtauration of the <hi>Iewes</hi> after their captivity.
Both were written by <hi>Ezra,</hi> and of old called
<hi>the firſt and ſecond booke of Eſdras:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apud Hebraeos Eſdrae, Neem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſermones in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unum volumen coartantur. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron in Eſd. &amp; Neem praeſat. <hi>Ezr.</hi> 2. 2.—3. 8.</note> yea by
the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> they were both brought into one
Volume.</p>
            <p>For the foreſaid end of ſetling the State of the
<hi>Iewes</hi> there were three ſolemne commings of three
famous perſons to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> The firſt was of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbabel,</hi>
who being a young man laid the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Temple in the reigne of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
an old man finiſhed it in the reigne of <hi>Darius.</hi>
The ſecond was of <hi>Ezra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—6. 15.</note> 
               <hi>a ready Scribe in the Law
of</hi> Moſes,<note place="margin">—7. 6.</note> whoſe comming was<note n="*" place="margin">After the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of the Iews <hi>Cyrus</hi> raigned nine years, One <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius 36. Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuerus</hi> 22. One <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> 40. Another <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> 19 Another <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> 7. before <hi>Ezra</hi> came. Neh. 5. 1. &amp;c.—13. 4.</note> about one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
thirty and three yeares after the firſt, in the
ſeventh yeare of <hi>Artaxerxes.</hi> He came to inſtruct
the <hi>Iewes</hi> in the Law of God. The third was of
<hi>Nehemiah,</hi> thirteene yeares after <hi>Ezras.</hi> The end
of his comming was to build up the City of God
and the wall thereof, that Gods people might ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
more freely obſerve Gods Ordinances, and live
in ſafety and ſecurity from their enemies. When
he came thither he found many Grievances in the
State, and corruptions in the Church. <hi>Thoſe</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed,
<hi>theſe</hi> he remooved: and withall ſetled
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155989:6"/>
the <hi>Sabbaths Sanctification.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ne. 13. 15, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To ſhew whence he received his courage to doe
what he did, notwithſtanding the ſtrong and great
oppoſitions againſt him, it is oft noted in this book,
that his heart was on his God, to whom on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions
he preferred his prayer in the beginning, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe
and end of all.</p>
            <p>So ſoone as he heard of an occaſion of going to
<hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 1. 4. &amp;c.</note> he made his prayer to God. It was the
firſt thing he did. Ever and anone was his heart
lift up unto God in the Progreſſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Neh. 2. 4.—4. 4.—4. 9.—5. 19.—6. 14.—13. 14.—22.—29.</note> Eight parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
inſtances therof betwixt his firſt and laſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
are expreſly noted in this Hiſtory. This Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
is concluded with the ſame prayer that is in
my Text.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how my Text is inſerted in the
midſt of this Hiſtory, as a Demonſtration of the
Support whereon this Patriot reſted, and whereby
he was encouraged in his good, great, difficult, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
attempts.</p>
            <p>May I in this Auditory have leave to give, <hi>meo
more &amp; modo,</hi> after my ordinary and plaine manner,
the <hi>Grammaticall</hi> Interpretation and <hi>Logicall</hi> Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
of the Text, a more ready way will be made
thereby for raiſing and proſecuting proper <hi>Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi>
Obſervations thereout.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> therefore of the ſence.</p>
            <p>The word tranſlated, <hi>Thinke,</hi> properly ſignifieth
<hi>Remember.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 1. 8.—6. 14.—13. 14.—22.—29.—31.</note> So it is in other places tranſlated even
by theſe Tranſlators, and that ſix times in this book
applyed to God.</p>
            <p>It importeth two things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155989:6"/>
1. To keepe and hold faſt in mind and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
what is once knowne. So it is oppoſed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe:
as where the Law ſaith, <hi>Remember and
Forget not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 9. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2. To call againe to mind and memory what was
once knowne, but after forgotten: in which ſence
ſaith <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler,<note place="margin">Gen. 41. 9.—40. 23.</note> 
               <hi>I doe remember my faults this
day.</hi> He had forgotten his faults, his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
his dreame, the interpretation and iſſue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
(all which are implyed under this phraſe, <hi>The
chiefe Butler did not Remember</hi> Joſeph, <hi>but forgat
him</hi>) But by the wiſe mens ignorance of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreames, hee remembred and
called to mind his faults, and what followed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
            <p>In theſe two reſpects a word derived from this
root is put for <hi>a Memoriall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Exod. 28. 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eſt. 6. 1.</note> and for <hi>Records:</hi> by
which matters are ſo kept and retained, as they are
not loſt or forgotten: and by which if matters be
forgotten they may be againe called to mind, as
<hi>Mordecais</hi> faithfulneſſe to the King being forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
was by the Kings hearing the <hi>Records</hi> brought
to his mind.</p>
            <p>This act of <hi>Remembring</hi> is in ſacred Scripture ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
to God and man.</p>
            <p>To man properly in both the fore-mentioned
acceptions. As the two proofes doe ſhew. For
to man it was ſaid,<note place="margin">Deut. 9. 7. Gen. 41. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Remember and forget not:</hi>
and he was a man that ſaid, <hi>I doe remember my
faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To God it is moſt properly applyed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
ſignification. For he ever faſt holds in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155989:7"/>
and never forgets what he once knowes:<note place="margin">Act. 15. 18.</note> And
<hi>knowne unto God are all his workes from the beginning of
the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, alſo in the latter ſignification it is oft attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
to God,<note place="margin">Ier. 44. 21.</note> as where it is ſaid, <hi>Did not the Lord
remember them? and came it not into his minde?</hi>
The latter phraſe ſheweth that the act of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring
attributed to God in the former clauſe, is
ment of calling to mind what was formerly known.
<hi>Iob</hi> oft calleth on God to <hi>remember</hi> him in this ſence.<note place="margin">Iob 7, 7.—10, 9.—14, 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
In this reſpect God is ſaid to have <hi>Remembrancers:</hi>
to whom he thus ſaith, <hi>Put me in Remembrance:</hi>
and to this end he is ſaid to have a booke of <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Margin on Iſa. 62. 6. Iſa. 43. 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mal. 3. 16 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
But ſurely theſe things cannot be properly
ſpoken of God. They are to be taken <hi>tropically,</hi>
by way of reſemblance, after the manner of man.
When men having forgotten a friend, neglect him,
doe nothing for him, ſuffer him to want, to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
to lye in priſon, or remaine in captivity,
but being put in mind that he is ſuch and ſuch a
friend, doe good to him and ſuccour him, are ſaid
to remember him: So God (when after long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
his children to want ſuch and ſuch a bleſſing,
or to lye under ſuch and ſuch a croſſe, hee
beſtoweth on them the bleſſing which they ſo
long waited for or freeth them from the croſſe
under which they lay ſo long) though he never
forgat them, but knew and ſaw their want and
preſſure, is ſaid to remember them. Thus he <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred
Rachell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 30. 22. Exod. 2. 24.</note> who had long wanted a childe:
and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who had long lien under bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:155989:7"/>
In briefe <hi>Nehemiah</hi> by this phraſe, <hi>Thinke upon</hi>
or <hi>Remember,</hi> intendeth that God would ſo deale
with him, as he himſelfe might have aſſurance and
others evidence, that God did thinke upon what he
did and well remember it.</p>
            <p>This Petition he makes, not as doubting of Gods
good-will to him, but as reſting on God for ſome
evidence thereof. For what beleevers expect from
God they pray for: and what they pray for, with
confidence they expect to receive.</p>
            <p>To give further evidence of his ſpeciall aſſiance
on God, he reſtraineth this act of Gods good-will
to himſelfe in particular,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> by this clauſe, <hi>upon me,</hi>
and it carrieth this Emphaſis, that though the Lord
regarded not them who teſtified no hearty affection
to himſelf, his houſe or people, yet he would thinke
upon him whoſe heart was ſet on all theſe. <hi>Thinke
on me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next clauſe, <hi>my God,</hi> doth yet further ſet
out that his ſpeciall affiance on God.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>My,</hi> is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriating
particle: yet ſuch an one as admits o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
that are of like quality. Nor this, nor the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
particle of ſpeciality, nor <hi>Me,</hi> nor <hi>My</hi> is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
excluſively, as if he exempted all but himſelfe
from theſe priviledges, for before this, he deſireth
God to think on others like himſelf,<note place="margin">Neh. 1. 11.</note> thus, <hi>O Lord, I
beſeech thee, let now thine care be attentive to the
prayer of thy ſervant, and to the prayer of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
who deſire to feare thy name.</hi> And though
<note n="a" place="margin">Neh 28, 18.—6. 14.—7. 5. 13. 14, 15, 29, 31.</note> ſometimes he expreſſe the relation betwixt God
and himſelfe in the ſingular number, <hi>my God,</hi> yet
<note n="b" place="margin">Neh. 4, 4, 9, 20.—13. 18, 17</note> other times in the plurall number, thus, <hi>our God,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155989:8"/>
yea and in the ſecond and third perſons, thus,<note n="c" place="margin">Neh. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>your
God,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Neh. 13. 26.</note> 
               <hi>his God,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Neh. 12. 45.</note> 
               <hi>their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He uſeth the firſt perſon and ſingular number (<hi>my
God</hi>) to teſtifie the full aſſurance he had of his own
intereſt in God. He uſeth other perſons and the
plurall number (<hi>His God, Our God, Your God, Their
God</hi>) to intimate the ſtrong perſwaſion he had of
others like intereſt in God. The former is <hi>judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
certitudinis,</hi> an aſſured knowledge: the latter
<hi>judicium charitatis,</hi> a charitable belief. That theſe
two may ſtand together is evident by theſe phraſes
joyned together,<note n="f" place="margin">Ruth. 1. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Thy God ſhall be my God:</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 20. 17.</note> 
               <hi>I aſcend
to my God and your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the way take notice, that the mention which
I made of the ſingular number, hath reſpect to the
tranſlation,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>De iſtis decem nominibus lege</hi> Hier. <hi>Epiſt ad</hi> Marcel. See alſo the Churches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt on Exod. 17. 15. Sect. 72.</note> rather then to the originall, eſpecially
in the title <hi>GOD.</hi> For the Hebrew word is one
of thoſe ten titles which in ſacred Sacred Scripture
are as names attributed to God; and it is of the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
number. As all the other titles have their ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications
and myſteries, ſo this. It importeth a
plurality of perſons: yet ſo as in conſtruction it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timateth
an unity,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Verbatim Dij creavit. <hi>Gen</hi> 1. 1.</note> an unity in nature, the unity of
the Deity. For it is joyned with a verbe of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
number: as in the firſt ſentence of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
which in other languages may imply ſome
Grammaticall incongruity; but it expreſſeth a true
Orthodox, Theologicall Myſtery: which God
from the beginning would have to be knowne for
his owne glory and Churches good. For (even our
enemies, worſhippers of falſe gods being Judges)
our God is ſuch a God, as no other God could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155989:8"/>
be imagined like unto him. Many of Gods
incommunicable properties and workes have
(though moſt unjuſtly and falſly) beene attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to falſe gods, as<note n="h" place="margin">O Pater ô ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aeternae pote, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Virg. AEneid. 10.</note> eternity,<note n="i" place="margin">Te<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens Neptune in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voco, Cic Tuſc. l. 4.</note> omnipotency,
<note n="k" place="margin">Ovid Met l 1.</note> creation of Heaven and Earth,<note n="l" place="margin">Ovis nutu &amp; arbitrio coeum, terra, mart<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> reguntur, Cic ac Fin.</note> divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
and other the like. But it never came into
the mind of any Idolater to imagine his God to be
three in one. The <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>Vnity</hi> is a myſtery of
myſteries, making much to the honour of him that
is knowne and believed to be ſuch a God.</p>
            <p>By it alſo we know and beleeve that the <hi>Spirit</hi>
which proceedeth from the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> and
helpeth our infirmities, enableth us to doe the will
of God and eſtabliſheth us againſt all aſſaults, is
true God: and that the <hi>Sonne</hi> of God, the only
begotten of the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Mediatour</hi> betwixt
God and man, is true God: and that the <hi>Father</hi>
to whom we have acceſſe for all needfull bleſſing,
is true God. Thus we have not many gods for
many purpoſes; but one God for all turnes. One
to enable us to goe to the throne of grace: One to
mediate for us there: One to accept us there,
all one God. Is not this a comfortable my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie?</p>
            <p>But this by the way.</p>
            <p>That for which he deſireth his <hi>God to thinke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Sam. 7 28. 1 Kin. 8. 66.</note> is <hi>for good.</hi> The Hebrew word properly
ſignifieth <hi>goodneſse,</hi> and is ſo tranſlated in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
places, oft in the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and <hi>Prophets.</hi>
Some therefore here take it for a property in
God, and the cauſe or ground of his ſaith and hope,
and of all bleſſing: as if he had thus expreſſed it,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155989:9"/>
               <hi>Thinke on me for thy goodneſſe ſake.</hi> This is in it
ſelfe a good ſence, and anſwerable to this of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,
Remember thou me for thy goodneſse ſake ô Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 25. 7.</note>
But in my Text the particle of relation to God,
(<hi>Thy</hi>) is not expreſt, and the propoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
admits not that ſence.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In bonum.</note> Therefore the LXX.
Greeke Interpreters, the ancient Latine and ſundry
other tranſlate it as our Engliſh, <hi>for good:</hi> in like
manner is this very word with this prepoſition tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
(<hi>Gen.</hi> 50. 20.) <hi>unto good.</hi> Thus it ſets downe
the end why he would have God to thinke on him,
namely, ſome good, benefit, bleſſing to himſelfe.
That this is here intended, is further evident by
that which followes, <hi>according to all that I have
done,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Looke upon your books and yee will finde this
word, <hi>according,</hi> in another character, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
that it is not in the Originall, as indeed it is not.
Some therefore joyne theſe two words,<note place="margin">In bonum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quae feci.</note> 
               <hi>good, all,</hi>
together, thus, <hi>for good of all that I have done.</hi> This
expoſition might well ſtand,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Diſtinguit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det colon.</note> but that there is an
<hi>accent</hi> or <hi>pauſe</hi> annexed to the former word, which
diſtinguiſheth ſentences, or at leaſt the parts of a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.
Something therefore muſt be underſtood
to make up the latter part of this ſentence: and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
our Engliſh hath hit upon the fitteſt ſupplement,
as the ancient Latin,<note place="margin">Secundum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</note> and ſundry other languages.
The particle (<hi>according</hi>) here ſupplied, is oft on
like occaſions expreſſed,<note place="margin">Pſ. 62. 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as where the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith
to God, <hi>Thou rendereſt to every man according to his
workes.</hi> By this ſupplement no merit, but the kind
or quality, and meaſure or quantity of reward is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155989:9"/>
intended.<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7, 8.</note> In regard of the <hi>kinde, whatſoever a man
ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reape.</hi> He that ſoweth
wheat ſhall reape wheat: he that ſoweth tares ſhall
reape tares: <hi>He that ſoweth to his fleſh, ſhall of the
fleſh reape corruption: but he that ſoweth to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
ſhall of the ſpirit reape life everlaſting.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 6.</note> In regard
of the meaſure, <hi>He which ſoweth bountifully ſhall reap
bountifully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore he adds the next generall particle <hi>All,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
for All compriſeth many things under it, and exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
not any at all.</p>
            <p>That which he pleads of his owne doing in this
phraſe (<hi>that I have done</hi>) is not to be taken in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
to his owne ability in and of himſelf:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but to
the manifeſtation of the power of Gods Spirit in
him,<note place="margin">Zach. 4. 6. 1 Cor 15. 10.</note> which God himſelfe thus expreſſeth, <hi>Not
by might nor by power, but by my ſpirit,</hi> and Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> thus, <hi>I have laboured more abundantly then they
all: yet not I, but the grace of God which was
with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For further amplification of what he did, he ads
the perſons in whoſe behalfe he did all that he did,
<hi>for this people.</hi> He meanes hereby the <hi>Iewes,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
whom he then was, and thereupon as poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
at them, he uſeth a double demonſtrative par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,
as if to the full it had bin thus expreſſed,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>for
this people,</hi> even <hi>this.</hi> Well might he ſet this em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis
upon that people, becauſe at that time they
were the only Church of God,<note place="margin">Exod. 19. 5.</note> a peculiar treaſure
unto him above all people.</p>
            <p>Thus have you the plaine <hi>meaning</hi> of the Text.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of all in two words is,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:155989:10"/>
               <hi>Saints Support.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is in one word <hi>GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Support of Saints</hi> is ſet downe in forme of a
Petition.</p>
            <p>Therein is expreſſed,</p>
            <p>1. The <hi>Perſon</hi> petitioned.</p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Point</hi> prayed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Perſon</hi> is ſet out,</p>
            <p>1. By his generall title, <hi>GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. By his ſpeciall relation, <hi>MY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Point</hi> prayed for, ye may obſerve,</p>
            <p>1. The <hi>Kind</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The <hi>End</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kinde</hi> points at,</p>
            <p>1. An <hi>Act</hi> deſired of God, <hi>THINK VPON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The ſpeciall <hi>Object</hi> thereof, <hi>ME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>End</hi> is,</p>
            <p>1. Generally propounded, <hi>FOR GOOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Particularly amplified.</p>
            <p>In the amplification are diſtinctly ſet downe.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The</hi> Ground, THAT I HAVE DONE.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>The</hi> Rule, ACCORDING TO.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>The</hi> Extent, ALL.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>The</hi> Reſtraint <hi>or</hi> Limitation, FOR THIS
PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>Thinke upon me, my God, for good, <hi>according</hi> to
all that I have done for this People.</p>
            <p>The Obſervations hence ariſings are theſe.</p>
            <p>I. <hi>GOD is the Support of Saints.</hi> This Saint by
directing this his Petition to God, gives inſtance
hereof.</p>
            <p>II. <hi>The LORD is a peculiar GOD to a Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:155989:10"/>
This appropriating particle, <hi>MY,</hi> being ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
by a beleever in reference to God, evinceth
as much.</p>
            <p>III. GOD hath Remembrancers. <hi>He that ſaid to
God,</hi> thinke upon <hi>or</hi> remember, <hi>was ſuch an one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IV. <hi>GODS mind is ſoonest drawne to his owne.</hi>
He that could ſay, <hi>my God,</hi> was one of Gods owne
and thereupon was perſwaded to ſay to his God,
<hi>thinke upon ME,</hi> in confidence that God would
ſoon ſo doe.</p>
            <p>V. Prayer may be made for ones owne good. <hi>This
phraſe</hi> for good, <hi>intends as much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VI. <hi>Workes may be pleaded before GOD.</hi> So doth
he that in his prayer to God thus pleads, <hi>that I have
done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VII. <hi>Mans workes are the rule of Gods reward.</hi>
This is implied by the word fitly ſupplyed, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VIII. <hi>Every thing well done ſhall be rewarded.</hi>
This generall particle <hi>All,</hi> extends to every good
work, and intends ſuch an extent of reward.</p>
            <p>IX. <hi>Good done to GODS people is moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
Thus much is manifeſted, as by the expreſſion
of <hi>this people,</hi> ſo by the emphaſis added thereto, <hi>this
people,</hi> even <hi>this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the principall intendments of this
Text.</p>
            <p>That ye may the better diſcerne the true and juſt
ground of all theſe points, and eſpecially of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots
confidence, whereby he was enboldened to
put his God in mind, to <hi>thinke on him for good</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<hi>to all that he had done for his people.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155989:11"/>
it will not be impertinent, nor yet unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to give you a briefe view of ſuch particular acts
done by him, as are in this booke diſtinctly ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
from the beginning to my Text. Hereby yee
may have a pertinent patterne for Juſtification of
what ye have done, and direction for what remains
yet to be done: and withall ye may ſee in what
courſes and cauſes yee may with confidence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
on your God and ſay, <hi>Thinke on us our God
for good,</hi> according <hi>to all that we have done for
this people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. The firſt particular noted of him is an
inquiſitive diſpoſition after the State of the Church,
how it fared with her. So ſoone as he heard that
<hi>Hanani</hi> and others were come from <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 1. 2.</note> he <hi>asked
them concerning the Iewes, and concerning</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.
He himſelfe was in a ſafe and ſecure place:
He had the favour of the greateſt Monarch then
on Earth: yet he thought not that enough: hee
muſt know how the Church doth. By this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry
he came to know what otherwiſe, it may
be, he ſhould never have knowne: and then the
Church might have wanted all that good which
he did for it.<note place="margin">Ignoti nulla cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptilo.</note> What eye ſees not or eare heares
not, heart rues not. Naturall men are in a moſt
woefull plight: But becauſe they know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
of it, they are no whit mooved with
it, nor care to ſeeke any redreſſe for it. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
doe nothing for the Church, becauſe they know
nothing of the Church. Be we therefore inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive
after it.</p>
            <p>2. That which he heard of the Churches diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155989:11"/>
wrought much compaſſion in him:<note place="margin">Neh. 1. 4.</note> For he
<hi>ſate down and wept, and mourned certain dayes.</hi> By
this ſympathy he ſhewes himſelf a true member of
the Church.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 26.</note> 
               <hi>If one member ſuffer, all the members
ſuffer with it.</hi> This cannot but beſeem the beſt.
For of God himſelf it is thus ſaid,<note place="margin">Iud 10. 16. Iſa. 63. 15. Hoſ. 11. 8.</note> 
               <hi>His ſoul was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
for the affliction of Iſrael.</hi> In ſuch caſes <hi>his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells</hi>
are ſaid to <hi>ſound: and his heart</hi> to be <hi>turned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
him.</hi> Art thou Lord ſo affected, and afflicted at
our miſery, and we no whit moved with our own
or others diſtreſſes?<note place="margin">Amo. 6. 1, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Woe,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>woe to
them that are at eaſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that stretch themſelvs upon
their couches, and eate the Lambs out of the flock: that
chant to the ſound of the violl: that drink wine in
bowles, and annoint themſelvs with the chief ointments:
but they are not grieved for the affliction of</hi> Joſeph.
What good can be expected from ſuch ſenceleſſe
diſpoſitions? That compaſſion which was wrought
in this Patriot, ſet him on work, to do all that good
which he did for the Church. <hi>Let this mind be in you,
which was alſo in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Before he attempts any thing, he goes to
God. Firſt to God, then to the King. <hi>I prayed,</hi>
ſaith he,<note place="margin">Neh. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>before the God of Heaven.</hi> This made all
that he did ſo ſucceſſefull as it was. <hi>Saul,</hi> though
an hypocrite, could make this apology for his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſty
ſacrifice,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13. 12.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> Philiſtines <hi>will come down now
upon me to</hi> Gilgal, <hi>and I have not made ſupplication to
my God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Love princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium.</note> The very Heathen did uſe to begin all
with their God. Should not we Chriſtians ſo doe
with our God? I am confident ye ſo doe: and
thereupon with confidence I may ſay, Go on, and
proſper.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:155989:12"/>
4. He added one kind of prayer to another: to
his daily, ordinary prayers, he added extraordinary.
The phraſe of praying <hi>day and night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 1 6.</note> implies his
conſtant morning and evening prayer, wherein he
was ever mindfull of the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> His <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi>
was an evidence of extraordinary prayer.<note place="margin">—4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> This
particle, <hi>now,</hi> or <hi>this day,</hi> prefixed before <hi>day and
night,</hi> ſheweth that in this day of extraordinary
prayer helped by faſting, he omitted not his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
morning and evening devotion. Thus much
was prefigured in the Law.<note place="margin">Ex. 29 38, 39. Num. 28 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> For every day one
Lamb was to be offered <hi>in the morning,</hi> and another
<hi>at even:</hi> on their feaſt dayes they had other ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
ſacrifices enjoyned, yet ſo as with thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
ſacrifices they joyned their daily mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and evening burnt offering. In the 28. and 29.
Chapters of <hi>Numbers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 28. 10, 15, 23, 24, 31. &amp; 29, 6, 11, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 38.</note> where thoſe extraordinary
ſacrifices on their ſeverall dayes are expreſly ſet
down, this proviſo (<hi>beſide the continuall burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi>)
is fifteen times repeated. Ordinary and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
prayer joyned together, will adde life
and power each to other. Ordinary morning pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
may prove to be a good preparation to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
ordinance: and the evening ordinary
prayer a means of calling our failings in the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
to mind, of craving and obtaining pardon
for the ſame, and procuring a bleſſing in all. As for
extraordinary prayer quickned with faſting, it was
never performed (if at leaſt it were rightly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med)
without ſome more then ordinary bleſſing.
That Dvell, which cannot otherwiſe be caſt our,
may be <hi>caſt out by prayer and faſting.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 17. 21.</note> 
               <hi>What therefore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155989:12"/>
God hath joyned together, let no man put aſunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might here diſtinctly ſet out the particular
branches of his powerfull prayer, as,</p>
            <p>1. His ſolemn preamble,<note place="margin">Neh. 1. 5.</note> whereby he ſheweth
how his mind was ſo fixed on Gods greatneſſe and
goodneſſe as it had wrought a mixture of feare and
faith.</p>
            <p>2.<note place="margin">—6.</note> His humble confeſſion of ſinne: of his own
ſins, of the ſins of his fathers houſe, yea and of the
whole houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ 32. 5. Pro. 28. 13. 1 Ioh. 1. 9. Neh. 1. 8, 9.</note> This, penitently done, is
the ready way for obtaining mercy and pardon.</p>
            <p>3. His preſſing Gods own promiſe, whereby he
teſtifieth on what ground his faith was founded.</p>
            <p>4. His pleading that ſpeciall relation which was
betwixt God and them for whom he prayed, thus,
<hi>Theſe are thy ſervants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—10.</note> 
               <hi>and thy people.</hi> By this he gives
proof that the mark he aimes at is Gods glory.</p>
            <p>5. His putting God in mind of his former dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
with them, thus, <hi>whom thou haſt redeemed,</hi> &amp;c.
This ſhews, that by God himſelf, and his former
dealing with them, he is put on to commend their
cauſe to him.</p>
            <p>6.<note place="margin">—11.</note> His quickning of his own ſpirit, by his earneſt,
ardent expreſſion of his mind.</p>
            <p>But it being my purpoſe only to cull out ſuch
diſtinct acts of his as moved him to put God in
mind of him for good, it might hinder my purpoſe
to inſiſt on every particular circumſtance in thoſe
ſeverall acts, that are recorded of him.</p>
            <p>I return therfore to my principall purpoſe.</p>
            <p>5. His heart was ready on the ſudden to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to God. For when the King gave him occaſion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155989:13"/>
to make his mind knowne to him,<note place="margin">Neh. 2. 4.</note> he inſtantly <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to the God of Heaven:</hi> Not by turning aſide and
uttering any words to God, but by lifting up
his heart to God. This is called an ejaculation of the
ſpirit: when the ſpirit within a man caſteth up a
ſudden deſire to God. This ſudden deſire might
be, that God would direct him in ordering his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
to the King, and that God would encline the
Kings heart to grant his deſire. So much was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
thus expreſſed, <hi>Grant me mercy in the ſight of
this man,</hi> meaning the King. This may be as fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
and prevalent, as a ſolemne prayer uttered with
the mouth, witneſſe that ejaculation of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpirit,
when he was in the middeſt of the people, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging
them againſt <hi>Pharaohs</hi> furious hoſte that
hotly purſued them: He then uttered no words of
prayer, yet of that ejaculation, or inward deſire,
ſaith God,<note place="margin">Exod. 14. 15.</note> 
               <hi>why crieſt thou unto me?</hi> which phraſe
implyeth great fervency. This frequently and
heartily uſed argueth an heavenly mind, and holy
familiarity with God. This is one way whereby
we may pray <hi>alway, continually,</hi> even by the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of the heart to pray at all times, in all places,
on all occaſions, when we are alone, or in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
in conference, reading, ſtudying, working,
or doing any other lawfull thing. Thus may I now
in preaching, pray: thus may you even now in
hearing, pray. Aſſuredly, if we were well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
hereunto, we might have much better ſucceſſe
in many things we doe, then we have. What good
ſucceſſe had this Patriot hereupon? God mooved
the King to grant whatſoever he deſired.<note place="margin">Neh. 2. 8.</note> In ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155989:13"/>
in delivering Petitions to the King on earth,
<hi>Pray to the GOD of Heaven,</hi> as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did.</p>
            <p>6. Together with all ſorts of prayer to God,<note place="margin">Neh. 2. 5.</note> he
uſeth humane helps. He gratefully acknowledgeth
the Kings former <hi>favour:</hi>
               <note place="margin">—7.</note> He humbly ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<hi>leave</hi> to goe to <hi>Iudah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">—8.</note> he deſireth a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy:
he craveth the Kings <hi>Letters</hi> patent for all
uſefull and needfull Timber out of his Forreſts.
All theſe were lawfull meanes: and ſuch meanes
are the hand of Gods providence, whereby hee
bringeth matters to paſſe. It is true indeed, that
<hi>man liveth not by bread alone:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 8. 3.</note> meanes <hi>alone</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Gods bleſſing doe no good. <hi>Aſaes</hi> fault con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted
not ſimply in this,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 16. 12.</note> that in his diſeaſe he ſought
to the <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> but in this, that <hi>he ſought not to the
Lord</hi> A <hi>woe</hi> is denounced againſt thoſe <hi>that take
counſell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 1.—31. 1.</note> 
               <hi>but not of the Lord, and that cover with a
covering, but not of his Spirit.</hi> But true alſo it is,
that where meanes are meet to be uſed, God will
not bring matters to paſſe without meanes. In the
great danger wherein <hi>Paul,</hi> and all in the Ship with
him were, God promiſed that there ſhould be no
<hi>loſſe of any mans life among them:</hi> yet <hi>when the
Ship-men</hi> (who are an eſpeciall meanes of helpe in
feare of wreck) <hi>were about to fly out of the Ship,</hi> Paul
<hi>ſaid, except theſe abide in the Ship, ye cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
It will therefore be our wiſdome to obſerve
in the matters that we enterprize, what lawfull
meanes may be helpefull thereto, and with prayer
to uſe the ſame. By uſing meanes without prayer
we preſume: by praying without the uſe of means
we tempt God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:155989:14"/>
7. He goes himſelf to the place where he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to doe good.<note place="margin">Neh. 2, 11.</note> 
               <hi>I came to Ieruſalem,</hi> ſaith he. The
deſire that he had to have the worke throughly
don, moved him to goe himſelfe about it, and not to
put it off to others. If men of place and power,
who wiſh well to Church and State, were ſo min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
there would not be ſo many miſcarriages in
weighty matters,<note place="margin">2 King 4 30.</note> as oft fal out. The <hi>Shunamite</hi> would
not leave the Prophet, till he himſelfe went to her
childe. His ſervant went with his ſtaffe, but effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
nothing; When he himſelfe came, the deed
was ſoone done. A difference betwixt a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
that holdeth his land in his owne hands, and
ſcarſe raiſeth up ſo much as the ordinary rent
amounts to, and the Farmer, who beſide the rent,
raiſeth up a good livelihood, herein lyeth; That the
Gentleman lying in bed, or following his pleaſures,
ſaith to his ſervants, <hi>Goe Sirs,</hi> intending that they
ſhould goe about his worke: But the Farmer ſaith,
<hi>Gaw Sirs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oculus Domini paſcit equum.</note> that is, <hi>Goe we,</hi> together, or goe with
me. This Proverbe, <hi>the eye of the Maſter makes the
horſe fat,</hi> intendeth as much. This may be a good
patterne to you Governours, to us Miniſters, and
to all that have the charge of matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>8. He himſelfe taketh an eſpeciall view of the
ruines of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>I went out by night,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and
viewed the wals of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>which were broken
downe,</hi> &amp;c. He had heard thereof before: but now
he was an eye-witneſſe; and this increaſed his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,
enflamed his zeale, and ſtirred him up
more diligently and throughly to repaire the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155989:14"/>
and make up the breaches which he had ſeen
with his owne eyes. Sight of diſtreſſe is of great
force to worke on the affections, and to procure
ſuccour.<note place="margin">Luk. 10. 33.</note> The Samaritan <hi>who came where the wounded
man was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tu deſceude iudaginis ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, ne quid ſit quod ſallat, aut lateat. Ambx. de Pateiach. Abr l. 1. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaw him, had compaſſion on him,</hi> and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured
him. Doe ye likewiſe what ye can, to take
ſpeciall notice of the particular caſes of ſuch as are
in diſtreſſe, that nothing beguile you, nothing be
concealed from you. Goe to priſons, viſit the ſicke,
caſt your eyes on miſerable objects.</p>
            <p>9. He puts others in mind of that which he and
they ſaw:<note place="margin">Neh. 2. 17.</note> and ſtirres them up thereby to be aſſiſtant
to him, in theſe words, <hi>ye ſee the diſtreſſe that we are
in,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Come, and let us build up the wall,</hi> &amp;c. This he
did to ſtirre up ſuch a ſpirit in many others, as he
himſelfe had, and to obtaine their help: that ſo the
great worke might the better goe on. For <hi>many
hands make light worke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Multorum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus grande le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatur onus.</note> The fruit and benefit hereof
is diſtinctly ſet down in the third Chapter. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
thinke it not enough (in great matters, which
of and by your ſelves ye cannot to purpoſe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh)
think it not enough to doe, even to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
what lyes in your owne power: ſtir up others
to be aiding and aſſiſting to you. This juſtifies your
Proteſtation, your Subſidies, Pole-money, Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,
Loanes, and other meanes uſed for aſſiſtance
from others in the weighty works you have in hand.</p>
            <p>10. He manifeſteth invincible courage againſt
ſuch adverſaries as ſought to blaſt all his good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
and endeavours.<note place="margin">Neh. 2. 19 20.</note> 
               <hi>When</hi> Sanballat <hi>and others
laughed them to ſcorne, and deſpiſed them, he with a</hi>
confident ſpirit <hi>ſaid, The God of Heaven he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155989:15"/>
us; Therefore we his ſervants will ariſe and build.</hi>
Behold his courage, behold the ground thereof.
<hi>We will ariſe and build.</hi> O undaunted Spirit! <hi>God
will proſper us:</hi> a ſure and ſafe ground. If in any thing
ye imitate this Patriot, herein imitate him. Be not
diſcouraged by adverſaries.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Where God openeth a
great and effectuall doore to his ſervants, there will be
many adverſaries:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 28.</note> But <hi>in nothing be terrified by them:</hi>
and that ye may in nothing be terrified by them, ſo
place your confidence on God, as ye may in faith
ſay, <hi>The God of Heaven he will proſper us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Chapter diſtinctly deſcribeth the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
that was afforded by others in fencing the
City, and is an expreſſe demonſtration of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
of helpers, ſet downe in the ninth branch. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
paſſe over this Chapter, that I may haſten to
my Text.</p>
            <p>11. In an holy zeale, and juſt indignation, he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precates
vengeance againſt proud, ſcornfull, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable
enemies of Gods Church, in this manner,
<hi>Turne their reproach upon their owne head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and give
them for a prey in the land of their captivity, and cover
not their iniquity,</hi> &amp;c. I muſt confeſſe that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations
of holy men recorded in ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
are ſharp, two edged tooles: not for every ones
handling. When Chriſts Diſciples would have
<hi>commanded fire</hi> (as <hi>Eliah</hi> did) <hi>to come downe from
Heaven to conſume the</hi> Samaritans,<note place="margin">Luk. 9. 54. 55.</note> 
               <hi>he rebuked them,
and ſaid, Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of.</hi>
Particular imprecations againſt particular perſons
are not for every ſpirit; but for ſuch extraordinary
ſpirits, as Prophets and Apoſtles had: Yet thus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155989:15"/>
farre may every faithfull ſpirit teſtifie his holy zeal
in this very kind of imprecation, by an indefinite
extending it againſt ſuch as are indeed miſchievous
and irreconcileable enemies of the Church. But
becauſe <hi>Saul</hi> may prove a <hi>Paul,</hi> and a <hi>perſecutor</hi> may
prove a <hi>preacher</hi> of the Goſpell, we may not
imprecate againſt any particular perſons, yet againſt
their miſchievous practiſes we may.</p>
            <p>12. Them whom he incited to aſſiſt him, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged,
and that by the ſame ground of encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
whereby he himſelfe was encouraged.
He was encouraged by his confidence on God;<note place="margin">Neh. 2. 20.—4. 14.</note> and
thus he encourageth others, <hi>Be not ye afraid of them,
remember the Lord, who is great and terrible.</hi> To ſuch
a purpoſe tends this of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>God comforteth
us in all our tribulations, that we may be able to comfort
them which are in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith
we our ſelves are comforted of God.</hi> Ye that are ſtrong,
doe what ye can to ſtrengthen others: Ye whoſe
ſpirits are lofty and ſteddy, lift up and hold up the
ſpirits of others: put courage into others, ye that
are men of courage. This was Chriſts advice to
<hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 32.</note> 
               <hi>When thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>13. In an extraordinary caſe he uſeth extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
diligence and vigilancy.<note place="margin">Neh. 4. 8, 11, 12</note> The manifold miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous
plots of their adverſaries ſhewed their
danger to be more then ordinary.<note place="margin">Ver. 0, 16, 17, 20, 21, 23.</note> In this caſe, <hi>he ſet
a watch againſt them day and night: One halfe of his
ſervants wrought in the worke, the other halfe held of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive
and defenſive weapons. Every workeman
wrought with one hand, and with another held a weapon,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155989:16"/>
they had a trumpet to draw them all to the place of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;
they daily watched from the riſing of the Morning
till the Starres appeared: none of them put off their
cloathes, ſaving that every one put them off for waſhing.</hi>
Is not now the more then ordinary paines, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
looſing meales meat, defenſive proviſion, and
diligence uſed by our Parliament, is it not every
way warrantable and commendable? Have we any
cauſe to complaine thereof? Have we not juſt cauſe
to bleſſe God therefore?</p>
            <p>14. He redreſſes home-grievances. He thought
it not enough to ſecure the City from publike ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
unleſſe alſo he eaſed the common people from
the oppreſſion of their Governours.<note place="margin">Neh. 5. 1, &amp;c.</note> For <hi>there was
a great cry of the people and of their wives, againſt their
brethren the Iewes,</hi> who were Governours, and had
power over them. The particulars of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints
are expreſly related.<note place="margin">—6, &amp;c.</note> This good Patriot
heares them all, is much offended at the wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers,
adviſeth about redreſſe, and ſo orders the
matter, that for the wrong done, reſtitution and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
is made; and for the future, order is taken
that there be no more ſuch grievances.</p>
            <p>Ye that juſtly have obtained the name of <hi>good
Patriots,</hi> and have begun to redreſſe many grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
goe on in that good worke, till through Gods
bleſſing and your endeavours it be brought to ſome
good perfection, as <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> was. Heare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,
receive Petitions, examine Accuſations, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
Delinquents, cauſe reſtitution of that which
is uniuſtly taken away, and ſatisfaction for that
which is wrongfully done, to be made.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:155989:16"/>
Ye are now the great Judges of this land:<note place="margin">Iudex &amp; Ara idem: pariter enim ad utru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> confugiunt qui inturia afficiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Archite dict. <hi>Iob</hi> 29. 12.</note> and of
old it was ſaid, that the Altar and Iudge are as one,
in that ſuch as are wronged fly to the one and the
other for ſuccor. Such was <hi>Iobs</hi> practiſe. <hi>I delivered,</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>the poore that cryed, and the fatherleſse, and
him that had none to help him.</hi> Remembrance hereof
much comforted him againſt his friends unjuſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies
in the depth of his great miſeries.</p>
            <p>15. He relieved ſuch as were in diſtreſſe. It was
not a pharaſaicall brag, but a knowne truth, which
he thus profeſſeth of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Neh. 5. 8.</note> 
               <hi>We after our ability
have redeemed our brethren,</hi> &amp;c. To him it ſeemed
not ſufficient to redreſſe the wrongs which others
had done, and to take off the heavy burdens
which others had laid upon the backs of their
poore brethren (which was a great privitive good)
unleſſe alſo poſitively be relieved with money,
corne, and other neceſſaries, and that <hi>gratis,</hi> ſuch as
were in need.</p>
            <p>Hereby we ſee how farre our works of mercy
ought to extend. This to the life is thus exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
by a Prophet,<note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 6, 7.</note> in the name of the Lord: <hi>Is not
this the Faſt that I have choſen, to looſe the bands of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſse,
to undoe the heavy burdens, and to let the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
goe free, and that ye breake every yoake?</hi>
(Though this be moſt properly meant of redreſſing
ſuch wrongs, as men themſelves doe, yet may it
alſo be extended to redreſſing the wrongs which
others do; but for the point which we have in hand,
marke what followes) <hi>Is it not to breake thy bread to
the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are caſt out,
to thy houſe,</hi> &amp;c. This is the extent of charity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:155989:17"/>
16. He brought them to a ſolemne covenant and
oath to binde them to that good order that he had
made,<note place="margin">Neh. 5 12.</note> leſt they ſhould ſtart from it. It is thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
<hi>I tooke an oath of them that they ſhould doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to their promiſe.</hi> (Their promiſe was this, <hi>We
will reſtore them, and will require nothing of them: ſo
will we doe as thou ſayeſt.</hi>) Yea he made a terrible im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation
againſt every one that performed not this
promiſe. He feared leaſt in his abſence, when he
ſhould in the time limited returne to the King, they
would returne to their former exactions and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.
Therefore he would hereby reſtraine them.
A pious and prudent courſe. The like courſe we read
to be taken by <hi>Aſa,</hi> who bound his people by <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>
and <hi>Oath</hi> to remaine faithfull with the
Lord.<note place="margin">2 Chr. 15 12. &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is the rather to be noted for juſtification and
commendation of the courſe which both Houſes of
Parliament have taken, about bringing moſt of this
Land into a ſolemne Covenant. The Lord make
men faithfull in keeping it, and give a happy iſſue
thereto.</p>
            <p>17. For the peoples good in their neceſſity he
remitted of his own right. For he was by the King
<hi>appointed a Governour;</hi> and Governours had allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances
due to them, which former Governours had
taken: By reaſon hereof they were <hi>chargeable to the
people, and had taken of them bread and wine, beſide forty
ſhekels of ſilver</hi> (that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 5. 14, 15. Siclus S Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derabat ſtateremunum, ſeu ſemiunciam Shind.</note> five pounds ſterling; for a
ſhekell is halfe an ounce, which makes two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
ſixe pence: They exacted the foreſaid <hi>bread
and wine,</hi> that is, all manner of proviſion,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155989:17"/>
(<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Poſt argeti fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos, poſl quam accepiſsent ab eis 40 ſiclos ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti, olim con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituros ancibus pro victu ſuo. Vatabl Summumius ſumma tniuria. Ci. Offic l &amp; Orat pro Mur.</note> beſide the <hi>forty ſhekels,</hi> which was their ſet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance)
<hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>from the time that I was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to be their Governour, I and my brethren have not
eaten the bread of the Governour.</hi> He renders this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
hereof, <hi>becauſe of the feare of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They therefore that feare the Lord will be like
minded: they will not over-ſtrictly ſtand upon
their right, eſpecially in times of neceſſity, and
caſes of extremity. Over-ſtrict ſtanding upon right
may prove a great oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>18. He, though a Governour, did beare a part in
that which he required others to doe. <hi>I alſo,</hi> ſaith he,
<hi>continued in the worke of the wall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>neither bought we
any Land: and all my ſervants were gathered thither
unto the worke.</hi> He had done much for them through
the Kings favour to him,<note place="margin">Neh. 2. 8.</note> and through that power
and authority which the King had given him: For
he obtained for them as much timber as was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
out of the Kings Forreſt: He drew on others
that were able to help on the building of the wals:
He made ſpeciall proviſion for their ſecurity againſt
their adverſaries: He did many other good turnes
for them; yet ſo long as there remained any thing
which might further be done by him or his, all that
he had done, though it were much, ſeemed to him
too little.</p>
            <p>A worthy patterne this is to ſuch as have done
much good, to obſerve whether yet there be any
thing wherein they may doe more good,<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Let us not
be weary in well doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>19.<note place="margin">Rom 12. 13. 1 Pet. 4. 9. Neh. 5. 17.</note> He was <hi>given to Hoſpitality,</hi> and <hi>uſed it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
grudging.</hi> For <hi>there were at his Table one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155989:18"/>
and fifty of the</hi> Jewes <hi>and Rulers, beſides thoſe
that came unto them from among the Heathen.</hi> So
as he entertained all of all ſorts:<note place="margin">Heb. 13. 2.</note> ſuch as had their
habitations thereabouts, and ſuch as were ſtrangers
and came out of other countries. Thus he made his
entertainment not onely a worke of <hi>courteſie</hi> in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording
it to Neighbours and Rulers, who might
have provided for themſelves: but alſo of <hi>charity</hi>
in extending it to ſtrangers. How bountifull he
was therein is made evident by the daily proviſion
prepared for thoſe purpoſes, as <hi>one Oxe, ſix choice
Sheepe: alſo Foules once in ten daies, and ſtore of
all ſorts of wine.</hi> Hoſpitality to ſtrangers as well
as others,<note place="margin">Gen. 18. 1, &amp;c.—19. 1. &amp;c. Heb. 13. 2. Mat. 25. 34, 35.</note> is ſo acceptable to God, as he ſent <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>
with bleſſed tydings to be gueſts to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:
and Chriſt reckons up this worke of charity
in ſpeciall and by name among thoſe which he doth
moſt abundantly recompence.</p>
            <p>I will conclude this particular with that exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
which Chriſt gave upon anothers act of Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality,<note place="margin">Luk. 10. 37.</note>
               <hi>Goe and doe likewiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>20. Whatſoever hee did, hee did in reſpect to
God. Hee expected no reward from man: nor
did he propound any bie-ends to himſelfe: nor
did any thing on bie-reſpects. My Text gives a
plain demonſtration hereof. For therby we ſee that
his mind was fixed on his God. On God he cals to
think upon him, from God he expects his reward
for all that he had done. How many <hi>Nehemiahs,</hi> how
many good and zealous Patriots would this and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Kingdomes have, if we had many men of place
and parts ſo minded? Every one that minds God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155989:18"/>
in every good thing that he doth, and expects his
reward from him, in ſuch a way, after ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did, may with like confidence ſay
to God, <hi>Thinke on me my GOD for good,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<hi>to all that I have done for this people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this recollection of the principall acts of this
Patriot, you ſee what remarkable matters he did:
what difficulties and dangers hee paſſed thorow,
what encouraged and emboldned him to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
ſo many, mighty, malignant adverſaries
as he met withall, and what was the happy iſſue of
all. Hereby alſo you may further ſee what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
worthy Patriots to doe:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (virtutem intelligit) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Heſiod.</note> what dangers and
difficulties they may meet withall: (for what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
worke is not environed with many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
yea and dangers too?) with what courage
and conſtancy they ought to ſtand againſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
parties: on whom they may ſecurely place
their confidence: and on what ground any one
may ſay, <hi>Thinke on me, my GOD, for good,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<hi>to all that I have done for this people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I brought you againe to my Text:
which (as you heard before) affords many conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Obſervations. So much time hath bin ſpent
in ſetting out the patterne of a worthy Patriot, as
there can be no expectation of handling all the nine
Doctrines collected out of this Text. The firſt is
the chiefeſt of all and comprizeth the pith of all the
reſt within it. May I have liberty and ability to
touch upon it, I will give place to my reverend
Brother, that with greater ſtrength may hold out
the ſolemnization of this daies humiliation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:155989:19"/>
The firſt Obſervation is this,</p>
            <p>God is the Support of Saints.</p>
            <p>1. He is a <hi>Support,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>He</hi> is ſo to <hi>Saints,</hi> becauſe he is a <hi>peculiar God</hi>
to them.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Saints</hi> know it to be ſo, in that they are <hi>Gods
Remembrancers,</hi> and call upon him to <hi>thinke</hi> upon
them.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Saints</hi> with more confidence reſt on God for
Support, becauſe his mind is ſooneſt drawne to
them: whereupon every <hi>Saint</hi> ſaith to God, <hi>thinke
upon me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Their expectation of <hi>good</hi> from God further
ſhewes, that they take him for their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
            <p>6. Their pleading of their workes before God,
gives further proofe to the point.</p>
            <p>7. The rather in that their works are the rule <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording</hi>
to which God rewards them.</p>
            <p>8. And in that he rewardeth <hi>every</hi> good worke
of theirs.</p>
            <p>9. And finally, in that God hath moſt and beſt
reſpect to that which is done to <hi>his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how the eight ſubſequent Doctrins
have an eye to the firſt: ſo as I had cauſe to ſay,
that the firſt compriſeth the pith of all the reſt
within it. I come now directly and diſtinctly to
handle it by it ſelf. It is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God is the Support of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many, many Epithites attributed to him in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
Scripture, are as ſo many proofs of the point:
ſuch as theſe,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 14 6.</note> 
               <hi>Refuge,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">—31. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Houſe of defence,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">—6 13.</note> 
               <hi>Shelter,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:155989:19"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſ 18. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Fortreſse, high Tower, Buckler, Rocke,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">—119 114.</note> 
               <hi>Hiding place,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſa 49. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Saviour, Redeemer,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 40 17.</note> 
               <hi>Deliver</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">—54. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Helper,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder,</hi>
yea<note n="i" place="margin">Pſ. 27. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Salvation,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Redemption,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſ 115. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Help,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 15. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
great Reward.</hi> Theſe latter Epithites being
in the abſtract (whereby is ſhewed that all Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
Redemption, Helpe and Reward ariſe only
and wholy from him) add much Emphaſis to the
point.</p>
            <p>There are two eſpeciall grounds thereof.</p>
            <p>1. Saints taking God to be their Support.</p>
            <p>2. Gods undertaking to bee to his Saints,
what they take him to be.</p>
            <p>To him on all occaſions they have recourſe for
Support: and He anſwerably ſupporteth them that
have recourſe to him. He never faileth them that
ſeek him.</p>
            <p>Three things move Saints to take God for their
Support.</p>
            <p>1. The many enemies and dangers whereunto
they are here ſubject. This world is a wilderneſſe
of wild and ravenous Beaſts. All ſorts of wicked
men are thoſe wild and ravenous Beaſts: they are
as Lyons, Tigers, Bears, Wolves, and ſuch like.
Saints are as Sheepe and Lambes. In alluſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
ſaith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I ſend you forth as Sheepe in
the midſt of Wolves.</hi> This their condition in this
world makes them ſeeke for a Support.</p>
            <p>2. Their owne manifold infirmities by reaſon of
the fleſh which they carry about them. They are
(to uſe the woman of <hi>Tekoahs</hi> phraſe) <hi>as water ſpilt
upon the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14. 14.</note> 
               <hi>which cannot be gathered up again:</hi>
or to uſe a more pertinent compariſon, <hi>They</hi> are as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155989:20"/>
a Vine full of moſt ſweet and uſefull fruit, yet ſo
weake, as it cannot ſtand of it ſelf, without a frame,
or ſome other ſupport to beare it up. The weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of Saints makes them ſeek for a ſtrong ſupport:
which they know God to be.</p>
            <p>3. The impotency and diſability of any creature
to helpe and ſupport them.<note place="margin">Ezek. 20. 6, 7.</note> All creatures are as
reeds, weake, brickle, full of teeth: if they be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
upon they will ſoone breake and teare the fleſh
of ſuch as leane upon them. So as it is not onely
unuſefull and in vaine, but alſo dangerous and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageable
to reſt on meere creatures for a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
            <p>More then three things move God to be for his
Saints, what they take him to be: as</p>
            <p>1. That ancient love which of his owne good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will
he did beare to them before they were, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the worlds were. This doth the Apoſtle lay
downe as the ground of all thoſe ſpirituall bleſſings
wherewith God bleſſeth us, Eph. 1. 3, 4, 5, 6. This
he makes the ground of Gods <hi>quickning us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>and of his raiſing us up together,
and making us ſit together in heavenly places in
Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2.<note place="margin">1 Cor 6. 20 1 Pet. 1. 19. Heb. 9. 12</note> That price which the Sonne of God hath paid
for them, which was his own <hi>precious blood.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<hi>he obtained eternall redemption for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3.<note place="margin">Rom. 8 34. Heb 7. 25.</note> That continuall <hi>interceſſion</hi> which he maketh for
them at the right hand of his Father. Hereby hee
procureth continuance of Gods favour to them.</p>
            <p>4. That ſtamp or impreſſion of Gods image,
which the Holy Ghoſt hath ſet in them,<note place="margin">Eph 1 13.—4 30.</note> and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155989:20"/>
by they are <hi>ſealed unto the day of Redemption:</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
God knoweth them to be his.</p>
            <p>5. The many promiſes which God hath made
to them of caring and providing for them, and of
protecting them from all dangers and evils,<note place="margin">Heb. 10. 23.</note> and
<hi>faithfull is he who hath promiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. Their faith in reſting upon thoſe promiſes.
This makes them put God in mind thereof, as <hi>He</hi>
did,<note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 49.</note> who thus ſaid, <hi>Remember thy word</hi> (meaning
his word of promiſe) <hi>upon which thou haſt cauſed
me to hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Act of Saints in taking God for their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
is an evidence of that <hi>wiſedome and prudence
wherein God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Information in the wiſdom of Saints who take God for their ſupport. Eph. 1. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>according to the riches of his grace,
hath abounded towards them.</hi> For ſuch as are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to ſtand of themſelves, to ſeeke a Support, and
ſuch an one as of it ſelfe can ſufficiently ſupport
them, ſo as they need ſeeke to no others, is queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe
an eſpeciall part of prudence. But ſuch a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
the Lord is. For</p>
            <p>1.<note place="margin">1 Chr. 19 9.</note> The eyes of the Lord runne to and fro through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the whole Earth to ſhew himſelfe ſtrong in the
behalfe of them, whoſe heart is perfect towards him:
<hi>ſo as he is not, he cannot be ignorant of the needs
or diſtreſſes of any of his Saints.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 7.</note> I have ſurely ſeen
the affliction of my People, <hi>ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. As <hi>the eyes of the Lord are over the righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 12.</note>
               <hi>ſo his eares are open to their prayers.</hi> What cry ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
they make to him in their diſreſſe for ſuccour
and ſupport, he heareth.</p>
            <p>3. He is ready and forward to doe what he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
to be needfull and uſefull for them, <hi>I know their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155989:21"/>
ſorrowes, and I am come downe to deliver them,</hi> ſaith
the Lord to his people that were in diſtreſſe. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
promiſes hath he made for granting their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 15.</note>
The more to ſet out Gods forwardneſſe in
granting his Saints deſires,<note place="margin">Dan. 9. 23.</note> an <hi>Angell</hi> ſent from
God to <hi>Daniel</hi> while he was praying, thus ſaith, <hi>At
the beginning of thy ſupplication the Commandement
came forth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 24.</note> &amp;c. and the Lord himſelfe, thus, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they call I will anſwer, and whiles they are yet
ſpeaking I will heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 86. 15. Ier. 31. 20.</note> He is full of compaſſion: in ſo much as <hi>his
bowels are troubled</hi> for his children when they are in
any diſtreſſe: thereupon he maketh this inference,
<hi>I will ſurely have mercy upon them.</hi> Nothing ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
moves any to ſuccour and ſupport, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.
It is oft noted to be the cauſe of that ready
ſuccour which Chriſt in the daies of his fleſh affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to all that came to him, that he <hi>had compaſſion
on them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 14. 14.—15 30. ark. 1. 41.</note> and was <hi>moved</hi> therewith.</p>
            <p>5. Hee is able to ſupport his in their greateſt
weakneſſes,<note place="margin">Eph. 7. 13.</note> and to deliver them out of their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
diſtreſſe. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I am the Lord
the God of all fleſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 32. 27. Luk. 18. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Is there any thing too hard for
me? The things which are unpoſſible with men are
poſſible with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. As God <hi>is might in ſtrength,</hi> ſo in <hi>wiſedome.
His underſtanding is infinite.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 36. 5. Pſal. 147. 5.</note> He beſt knoweth when
to ſupport his and how: yea and how long to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
his ſupport to them. If at any time he ſeeme
to leave them to themſelves, he doth it purpoſely,
prudently, for good ends to good uſes. And even
then when he ſuffers them to lye under afflictions, he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155989:21"/>
ſo wiſely ſupporteth them, as they are enabled to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
it, and are not overburdened: Witneſſe he that
ſaid, <hi>We are troubled on every ſide, yet not diſtreſſed; we
are perplexed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>but not in deſpaire; perſecuted, but not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken;
caſt downe, but not deſtroyed:</hi> Yea through his
wiſedome (<hi>as at first he commanded the light to ſhine
out of darkneſse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 6.</note> ſo) he bringeth much good to
Saints out of their troubles. <hi>For we know that all
things worke together for good to them that love God.</hi>
This by good experience he found to be true in
himſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 7.</note> who ſaid, <hi>It is good for me that I have been
afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations of the notice that God hath
of his peoples ſtate and caſe, of his hearing their
prayers, of his forwardneſſe to grant their deſires, of
his compaſſion at their diſtreſſe, of his power and
ability to help, and of his wiſedome in ordering the
ſeaſon and manner of ſuccour: Theſe and other like
conſiderations give a cleare and evident demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that God is a ſafe, ſure, and ſecure ſupport,
whereby the wiſedome of Saints is manifeſted in
taking him for their ſupport. In this therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
as in many others,<note place="margin">Deut 4. 6.</note> it may be ſaid of them,
<hi>Surely this is a wiſe and understanding people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide,<note place="margin">2 Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their folly who take not God for their ſupport.</note> it muſt needs be a part of egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
folly and plaine dotage, to confide in, or truſt
unto any other ſupport then this God. Yet moſt in
the world are ſuch doting fooles: As,</p>
            <p>1.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> who <hi>ſay in their hearts there is no
God.</hi> Surely they who deny him to be, will not reſt
on him for ſupport.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Pagans,</hi> who being ignorant of the one onely
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155989:22"/>
true God, place their confidence on ſuch things as
never were, never had any true being, but were
meere phantaſies and imaginations of mens vaine
braine. Such as <hi>Baalim, Aſhteroh, Dagon, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi>
and ſuch other as are mentioned in ſacred
Scripture: And <hi>Iupiter, Iuno, Apollo, Diana, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,
Venus,</hi> and multitudes of the like reckoned
up by the heathen.<note place="margin">Heſiod in Osoyor.</note> One of their Poets reckoneth up
about thirty thouſand of them: Others more.</p>
            <p>3.<note place="margin">Purch. Pilgr. <hi>of</hi> Aſia, l. 4. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Indian Savages,</hi> who make the Devil their
ſupport, and adore him, that he may not hurt them
and their cattell. A part of their countrey is called
<hi>Terra Diaboli,</hi> the <hi>Devils Land.</hi> To retort upon
theſe in their owne kinde, Not onely <hi>no hurt,</hi> but
<hi>good,</hi> is to bee expected from ſuch as are adored, as
it is in my Text, Thinke upon me <hi>for good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who make the innumerable company
of Angels, the bleſſed <hi>Virgin Mary, Apostles, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,
Martyrs,</hi> and all that their Popes have cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized:
Whereof ſome may be accounted, ſuch as
the forementioned Gods of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> meere <hi>phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies</hi>
and imaginations; and others, without breach
of charity, may be judged to be damned wretches
in Hell.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>Worldlings,</hi> who reſt on mortall men, and
earthly meanes, which are all like to the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
weake reed full of teeth.<note place="margin">Iſa. 31. 1.</note> The Prophet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth
a <hi>woe</hi> againſt ſuch.</p>
            <p>6.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 21. and 17. 1, &amp;c. 1 Sam. 17. 8. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Self-boaſters,</hi> who truſt to themſelves, to their
owne parts, or to that command which they have
over others: As <hi>Achitophel</hi> who relyed on his own
wit;<note place="margin">Iſa. 10. 8, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Goliah</hi> on his owne ſtrength; the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> on
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155989:22"/>
the great command which he had: ſo others to other
things; all which turne to their ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of all theſe, and others like to theſe, I may, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the caſe in hand, take up the Prophets pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall
Exclamation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 2. 12, 13.</note> Be aſtoniſhed, O ye Heavens at
this and be ye horribly afraid, be ye very deſolate, ſaith
the Lord: For my people have committed two evils;
they have forſaken me the fountaine of living waters,
and hewed them out ciſternes, broken cisternes that can
hold no water.</p>
            <p>As for you that have been ſo farre enlightened
as to know God to be the onely ſure and ſafe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,<note place="margin">3 Exhortation to uſe God as a Support.</note>
and thereupon have been moved to take him
for your ſupport, be now further in the name of this
God exhorted, to uſe him as a ſupport. Uſe him as
a <hi>Refuge, Shelter, Houſe of Defence, Fortreſſe, high
Tower, Buckler, Shield, Rock, Hiding place.</hi> Theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances
will affoord good help for making a
right uſe of the Lord in this very point, as he is a
ſupport to his Saints.</p>
            <p>1. A <hi>refuge</hi> is a place for ſuch as are in danger to
fly unto for ſuccour and ſecurity. Such were the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of Refuge among the Jewes. When a man was
unjuſtly ſuſpected of wilfull murder, and hotly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued
by the avenger of bloud, he made all the ſpeed
he could to the City of Refuge. There was his
cauſe rightly judged, there might he be ſecure. Doe
you alſo fly to God in all undue ſuſpicions and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
accuſations. In him you may be ſure to have
your cauſe righted, and your perſons ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>2. A <hi>Shelter</hi> is for ſuch as in their journey are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:155989:23"/>
taken with ſhowres of rain, with haile, ſnow, ſtorm
or tempeſt: In ſuch caſes, if a traveller eſpy a ſhelter,
he will make haſte to it. God hath undertaken to be
<hi>a covert from storme and raine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 4 6.</note> When the raging
raine of oppreſſion, or ſtorme of perſecution, or
violent tempeſt of any malignant oppoſition fals
upon you, ſhelter your ſelves under the covert of
your God.</p>
            <p>3. An <hi>Houſe of Defence,</hi> or <hi>Caſtle,</hi> or <hi>Fortreſſe,</hi> or
<hi>High Tower,</hi> are all for ſafety againſt armies of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
that compaſſe us about, and beſiege us, and
would utterly deſtroy us, if we had not ſuch a place
of ſafety. Now the Lord is indeed an high and
ſtrong Tower, an impregnable Caſtle: abide there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
in him, and feare not, though multitudes of
enemies doe on every ſide ſet againſt you. They are
ſafe whom the Lord doth keep.</p>
            <p>4. A <hi>Buckler</hi> or <hi>Shield</hi> is of ſingular uſe to keep
off puſh of pike, ſtroake of ſword, force of dart,
arrow or bullet that ſhall be flung, or ſhot againſt us:
So faith in God will keep off all aſſaults of Satan,
even all the <hi>fiery darts of the Devill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 16.</note> much more the
furious, envious, and malicious words and deeds of
wicked men.</p>
            <p>5. A <hi>Rocke</hi> is a firme and ſure foundation. An
edifice that is well erected and ſetled on it, cannot
be overthrowne.<note place="margin">Mat 7 24, 25.</note> Though <hi>the raine deſcend and the
flouds come, and the wind blow, and beat upon that houſe,
yet it fals not becauſe it is founded on a rock.</hi> For appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
of this Metaphor, note what Chriſt ſaith of
himſelfe as he is a rocke:<note place="margin">Mat 16. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Vpon this rocke will I build
my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt
it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:155989:23"/>
Againe, a rock being in the Sea remains immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able:
The ſtrongeſt tempeſts and violenteſt waves of
the Sea cannot ſhake it, much leſſe overthrow it.
If therefore any who have ſuffered ſhipwracke lye
floating on the Sea, and eſpye a rocke, they will
make to it: ſo in our greateſt troubles, and moſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
dangers, let us get to God the rocke of our
ſalvation, and we may be ſure to be ſafe.</p>
            <p>6. An <hi>hiding place,</hi> is that wherein in many beaſts doe
repoſe themſelves on all occaſions: As a Connies
burrow, a Foxes hole, a Lyons den: when they are
there they thinke themſelves ſafe: There therefore
they uſe to ſleep; there they uſe to carry the prey
they get, and there to eat it: if they be hunted, or
fear any danger, they wil make thither as faſt as they
can: If they be hurt or wounded, there they uſe to
licke themſelves whole: yea in theſe their hiding
places they die for the moſt part, if at leaſt they be
not ſurpriſed, and kild when they are out of their
den or hiding place. Seeing it pleaſeth the Holy
Ghoſt to attribute unto God this reſemblance of<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 114. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
ſafety (For the Pſalmiſt ſtileth God his <hi>hiding place:</hi>
and the Prophet a <hi>covert</hi>) give me leave in Chriſts
phraſe to ſay unto you,<note place="margin">Latibulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meum. <hi>Iſa</hi> 4. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Behold the beaſts of the field:</hi>
Behold them in this particular,<note place="margin">Abſcontio.</note> and uſe God your
hiding place, as they uſe their holes and dennes.
On all occaſions repoſe your ſelves on him, and reſt
ſecure in him when ye ſleep, when ye wake. Have
ye good ſucceſſe in your affairs? (as the beaſt thinks
he hath when he gets a prey) goe to God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
in him, and to give the praiſe to him. Doe thy
affaires ſucceed ill? even then alſo goe to God, to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:155989:24"/>
mourne in him, to powre out thy ſoule into his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.
Art thou hunted or perſecuted? fly
to God for ſuccour and protection. Art thou abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
wronged, or hurt? To God for redreſſe and
right. In peace and trouble, in hope and feare, in
ſafety and danger, in all caſes, on all occaſions have
recourſe to God, live in God, die in God.</p>
            <p>Doe this the rather, becauſe as followeth in the
next obſervation.</p>
            <p>The Lord is a peculiar God to a beleever.</p>
            <p>But my time is ſlipt out, and I find my ſtrength to
faile, and you find my voice to fall, willingly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I give place to my reverend brother: Only let
us firſt call upon God for his bleſſing upon that
which hath been delivered, and give
him thanks for his gracious
aſſiſtance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
